In this demo, we'll be creating a program that utilizes structures.
Once you're ready, fire up Visual Studio Code, and let's go.
Once Visual Studio Code loads, navigate to your demo directory, or on these structures demo.
So scroll down to "Strucks" and double-click on "Strucks.go."
We'll make a small program that has passenger tickets and a bus, and the bus will indicate
who's in the front seat, and the passenger tickets will indicate whether or not they
boarded the bus.
So we'll create our first structure, we'll use the Type Keyword, and the name of our
structure for the first one is Passenger.
We follow up with the struct keyword and our curly braces, passengers are going to have
a name, they're going to have a ticket number, and whether or not they're boarded.
The next structure I'll make is the bus structure.
So again, we'll use the Type Keyword, this will be a bus, followed by the struct keyword, and
this is just going to indicate who is in the front seat of the bus, and this will be
a passenger.
So what we can do is we can have our front seats, the name of our variable, and Passenger
is the Type, and so we created our Type Alias here, which is a structure, so this passenger
refers to this entire structure up here.
We go down to our main function, we can start creating some passengers.
So the first passenger I'll create is named Casey, and I'll use the one line instantiation
technique, and so we'll just list out all the values for each field.
We should always print out some information that we know what we're working with.
Next, I'm going to create a few structures using the VAR keyword, and so we'll have Bill,
and I'll name the fields that I'm using, so we're going to use the name field, and
the ticket number field.
I'm not going to specify the other field, so I'm not going to specify the boarded field,
and that will have a default value, and the default for Boolean is false, so it's going
to be false by default, meaning they're not boarded, and we'll have the second one, and
this will be Ella, and their ticket number is going to be three.
And just like Casey, we'll print out these tickets out.
Next, I'm going to create an uninitialized variable, so I created one named Heidi, and
that's a passenger.
So right now, the fields for that particular structure are all defaults.
Next, I'll change the name, so we'll have Heidi's name, the Heidi, and we'll set her
ticket number to be four, and then print the ticket out.
Next, we're going to update some of the fields, so we'll update Casey's ticket, and
we'll set that he's boarded now, and we'll also have Bill B board on the bus.
We'll then access these fields again, and we'll do the same for Casey.
Next, we'll have Heidi board the bus, and she's our last passenger.
We'll then create a new bus, and we'll set Heidi to be the passenger that's in the front seat.
So we'll print out the bus.frontseat.name, just to confirm that Heidi is
indeed in the front seat.
Once all that's done, we can save and run, and see what kind of messages we have.
I'll be hopping into a terminal.
We can run this program with go run dot slash demo slash trucks.
And so here we have our three tickets that we made in the beginning.
So we have Casey, Bill, Ella, and then the fourth ticket is Heidi.
We then have Bill and Casey board the bus.
We change Heidi's boarded status to true.
And then we also print out some information from the bus structure.
So Heidi is indeed in the front seat.
If we jump back to our code, we can access Heidi's information.
We used bus and then access the front seat field and then access the name field.
So we have the bus variable, the front seat field in the bus structure,
and then the name field in the passenger structure.
So we're accessing the bus dot front seat, which is the passenger.
And since that's a passenger, we can then access dot name.
So depending on how deep your nesting structure is,
you just keep doing dots and eventually you'll get to the data that you need.
This concludes the demo on structures.
I'll see you in the next presentation.